Finding Aid for First Congregational Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.) Records, 1876-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First Congregational Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.) Records 1876-2002
First Congregational Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.)
86763 Ba 2
Historical materials; annual reports; minutes of meetings of boards and councils of the church; records of church societies and organizations; newsletters; and miscellaneous photographs and topical files.
4 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group is on deposit from the church (Donor no. 2033 ) and came to the library in 1944 and 2001. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open to research.
Congregationalists in Ypsilanti were part of the First Presbyterian Church until October 4, 1881, when a substitute pastor named Rev. George H. Grannis inspired them to establish a church of their own. The First Congregational Church of Ypsilanti broke ground at the corner of Adams and Emmet for a new building, which they dedicated on July 10, 1883.
In 1885, Rev. Miner W. Fairfield succeeded Grannis as pastor of the church. He chaired the first annual meetings and supervised the adoption of the Constitution of the Church, the Confession of Faith, and other documents which defined the new congregation.
Despite a succession of pastors during the late 1880s and 1890s, the membership continued to grow. In 1898, the builder Frank Norton remodeled and expanded the church facilities to include seating for 425 people; an annex for Sunday School and Bible study classes; and a basement with a dining room, a kitchen, and an assembly room.
The next fifty years were a time of growth and gradual development. In 1948, the First Congregational Church had 438 members, a budget of $9000, and eleven active organizations. By 1958, the church had grown to 657 members. Rev. Gordon C. Speer, pastor from 1938 to 1959, presided at the 75th Anniversary of the church. Under his successor, Dr. John W. Metler (1959-1963), the church bought a new parsonage at 707 Oakwood Avenue, and in 1962, the congregation agreed to join the United Church of Christ.
During the late 1960s and 1970s, the congregation began to address several social issues, including civil rights, gender-inclusive language, and role of children in church activities. Tension over the pastorate of John and Nancy Rohde led to a decline in membership in 1982, but the congregation gradually recovered in the following years, and it dedicated a new addition to the church in 1988. During the late 1980s and early 1990s, the First Congregational Church maintained its commitment to social activism.
The records of the First Congregational Church of Ypsilanti date from 1881 to 1999, and include annual reports; minutes of meetings of boards and councils of the church; records of church societies and organizations; newsletters; and miscellaneous photographs and topical files. The records are divided into five series: History and Church Records, Reports and Meetings, Organizations and Societies, Newsletters and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Congregational churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Women--Michigan--Ypsilanti--Societies and clubs.; Ypsilanti (Mich.); Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; First Congregational Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
First Congregational Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Churches.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History and Church Records
  The History and Church Records series contains the history of the church written by Frederick B. Mckay in 1961. It also contains the church constitution and a manual of the church from 1886. In addition, the series contains the Clerk's records and the Church register and record, which contains lists of members, officers, deacons, baptisms and statistics.
  - History
    - 1881-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1991 (Box 1)
  - Constitution and By-laws 1962, 1976, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Benevolence Treasurer's Record 1936-1965 (Box 1)
  - Clerk's Record 1886-1939, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Church Register and Record 1881-1913, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - First Membership List of Church (Box 1)
  - Proposed Plan for Church Renewal 1984 (Box 1)
- Reports and Meetings
  The Reports and Meetings series contains Annual Reports from 1947 to 1992. The series also contains minutes from the meetings of boards and councils of the church, such as the Advisory Council and the Board of Trustees. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Annual Meetings
    - 1883, 1889, 1892, 1931 (Box 1)
    - 1961, 1962, 1969, 1973, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1947-1960, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - 1966-1979, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1980, 1986, 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Council Meetings 1964-1984 (except 1975), 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Board of Christian Education Meetings 1972-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Board of Deacons Meetings 1962-1984, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees Meetings
    - 1912-1930, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1947-1950 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1984, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Church Council Meetings 1985-1999, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Congregational-Presbyterian Cooperative Committee Meetings 1969 (Box 2)
  - General Association of Michigan Meeting 1876 (Box 2)
- Organizations and Societies
  The Organizations and Societies series is arranged alphabetically and contains minutes and some historical sketches of the organizations and societies that have been part of the church.
  - Congregational Women's Guild
    - Historical Sketch 1945 (Box 2)
    - Minutes
      - 1932-1950 (except 1936), 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1951-1976, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Treasurer's Record 1928-1941 (Box 3)
  - Esther Guild 1955-1963 (Box 3)
  - Junior Christian Endeavor 1904-1905 (Box 3)
    (also include records of Ladies Aids, 1915)
  - May flower Guild Historical Sketch 1989 (Box 3)
  - Priscilla Guild 1942-1948 (Box 3)
  - Women's Fellowship Society 1960-1967 (Box 3)
  - Women's Missionary Societies
    - Historical Sketch (Box 3)
    - Women's Home Missionary Society
      - 1882-1904 (Box 3)
      - 1918-1924 (Box 3)
    - Women's Foreign Missionary Society 1904-1924 (Box 3)
    - Women's United Missionary Society 1925-1938 (Box 3)
  - Young People's Society 1886-1900 (Box 3)
  - Young Women's Guild 1916-1923 (Box 3)
- Newsletters
  The Newsletters series contains monthly newsletter "Congregating" which has information about church's activities and a message from the pastor. The series also includes correspondence sent to church members from the church clerk and from the board of trustees.
  - "Congregating" Newsletter
    - 1960-1963, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1964-1995, 24 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence to members from the Board of Trustees 1943-1948, 1953-1957 (Box 3)
    (lacking 1943, 1947, 1954 and 1956)
  - Correspondence to members from Church's Clerk 1961-1969 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series is arranged alphabetically and contains information about the pastors of the church during the period 1959-1989. The series also contains early photographs of pastors and other church members. There is also a scrapbook with clippings about members' weddings and members that passed away. Three record books from the Sunday School are also part of this series.
  - Anniversaries (Box 3)
  - Bulletins (Box 3)
  - Clippings 1885, 1920, 1979, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Memorials and other writings (Box 3)
  - Pastors
    - Rev. John Metler 1959-1963 (Box 3)
    - Rev. John Adams 1963-1966 (Box 3)
    - Rev. Jack D. Fitzgerald 1967-1972 (Box 3)
    - Rev. Ron Eslinger 1973-1979 (Box 3)
    - Revs. John and Nancy Rohde 1980-1989 (Box 3)
    - Pastoral Clippings 1946, 1949, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Pastoral Search Correspondence 1962, 1973, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
    Portraits of church ministers; interior view of the church, ca. 1905; portraits of church benefactors
  - Prayers (Box 3)
  - Sunday School Record 1921-1922, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1960-1969 (Volume 1)
  - Stained glass window survey 2002 (Box 3)